Haipeng Yu April 2020

CONTACT Information 3695 Litton Reaves Hall 175 West Campus Drive Virginia Tech

Blacksburg, Virginia 24061 USA

E-mail: haipengyu@vt.edu Phone: (701) 730-1368 WWW: haipengu.github.io

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My overarching research interest is to leverage statistics, machine learning, and bioinformatics to better understand the genotype-phenotype map in animal and plant genetics. Particularly, I am interested in developing and applying statistical methods to the whole-genome prediction of complex traits, genome-wide association analysis, high-throughput phenotyping analysis, and image analysis.

# EDUCATION

#### Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

Ph.D., Animal and Poultry Sciences - Quantitative Genetics, May 2020

- Dissertation: "Designing and modeling high-throughput phenotyping data in quantitative genetics" [Virginia Tech Libraries]
- Advisor: Dr. Gota Morota

#### North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

M.S., Animal Breeding and Genetics, August 2016

- Thesis: "The exploration of a four-platform standing scale in the application of measuring temperament in beef cattle"
- Advisor: Dr. Lauren Hulsman Hanna

## Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao, Shandong CHINA

B.S., Veterinary Medicine, July 2013

# Work Experience

Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

• Graduate Research Assistant

08/2018 - Present

• Graduate Teaching Assistant

Spring, 2019 and 2020

Department of Animal Science

University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska USA

• Graduate Research Assistant

08/2016 - 08/2018

Department of Animal Sciences

North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

• Graduate Teaching Assistant

08/2015 - 05/2016

• Graduate Research Assistant

01/2015 - 05/2016

Professional society memberships • The American Society of Animal Science. 2017 - Present

Preprints

- 7. Yu H, Morota G, Celestino EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, Riley DG, and Hanna LLH. Deciphering cattle temperament measures derived from a four-platform standing scale using genetic factor analytic modeling. bioRxiv. doi: 10.1101/2020.01.20.913343
- Campbell M, <u>Yu H</u>, Momen M, and Morota G. Examining the relationships between phenotypic plasticity and local environments with genomic structural equation models. bioRxiv. doi: 10.1101/2019.12.11.873257
- 5. Yu H and Morota G. GCA: An R package for genetic connectedness analysis using pedigree and genomic data. *bioRxiv*. doi: 10.1101/696419

# PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL PAPERS

3 first author and 1 co-author

2019

- 4. Hanna LLH, Hieber JK, <u>Yu H</u>, Celestino Jr EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, and Riley DG. 2019. Blood collection has negligible impact on scoring temperament in Angus-based weaned calves. *Livestock Science.* 230:103835. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2019.103835
- 3. Yu H, Campbell MT, Zhang Q, Walia H, and Morota G. 2019. Genomic Bayesian confirmatory factor analysis and Bayesian network to characterize a wide spectrum of rice phenotypes. *G3:* Genes, Genomes, Genetics. 9:1975-1986. doi: 10.1534/g3.119.400154

2018

Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. 2018. Do stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units? *Journal of Animal Science*. 96:4490-4500. doi: 10.1093/jas/sky316

2017

1. Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. 2017. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics. 10:3543-3556. doi: 10.1534/g3.117.300151.

### Papers in Proceedings

1 first author

2018

1. Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. 2018. Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. In: Proceedings, 11th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production. 11:406. February 11-16, Auckland, New Zealand. [PDF]

# CONTRIBUTED PRESENTATIONS

2019

4. Precision agriculture on cattle temperament: Utilizing factor analysis and multi-trait modeling to characterize a four-platform standing scale. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Blacksburg, VA. October 10-11.

2018

3. An assessment of genomic relatedness across management units. ADSA-ASAS 2018 Midwest Meeting. Omaha, NE. March 12-14. [Abstract]

2017

- 2. Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Stanley Stout Livestock Marketing Center, Manhattan, KS. October 18-19.
- 1. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. ASAS-CSAS Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Baltimore, MD. July 8-12.

#### Intramural Seminars

2019

- Genetic connectedness across management units. Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. May 21.
- Genetic connectedness across management units. The Reproductive Biology Club. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. April 19.

2018

• Genomic factor analytic and graphical models to characterize a wide spectrum of rice phenotypes. Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. February 28.

2017

- Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. February 14.
- The exploration of a four-platform standing scale in the application of measuring temperament in beef cattle. Animal Breeding and Genetics Seminars. Department of Animal Sciences, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. September 29

2016

• M.S., Thesis Defense. Department of Animal Sciences, North Dakota State University. May 17.

#### TEACHING

# Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, USA

# Guest Instructor

• GWAS Workshop [Slide]

**Summer 2019** 

# Graduate Teaching Assistant

• APSC 5984/20816: Complex Trait Genomics [WWW]

**Spring 2020** 

• ALS 3104: Animal Breeding and Genetics

Spring 2019

University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska, USA

#### Guest Instructor

• ASCI 944 / STAT 844 Quantitative Methods for Genomics of Complex Traits Spring 2018 [Slide] [R]

## North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA Graduate Teaching Assistant

• ANSC 357: Animal Genetics

Spring 2016

• AGRI 189: Skills for Academic Success

Fall 2015

### OSS

CONTRIBUTIONS

#### R package

• GCA - https://github.com/HaipengU/GCA

# PARTICIPATION IN MEETINGS, SYMPOSIUMS, AND WORKSHOPS

2015

- NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. North Dakota State University, ND, October 22-23.
- Graduate Learning Conference for College Teaching. North Dakota State University, ND. August 17-18.
- WERA-1: Beef Cattle Breeding in the Western Region. Miles City, MT. May 19-20.
- Midwest Meeting of American Society of Animal Science. Des Moines, IA. March 15-18.

### Honors/ Awards

2019

- 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG) Scholarship, University of Washington, July.
- Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium Travel Award \$400, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, May.

2015

• Frank Bain Graduate Student Scholarship \$1,650, North Dakota State University, Spring.

2009-2013

• Outstanding Undergraduate Scholarship, Qingdao Agricultural University, China.

# Additional Training

Deep Learning for Computer Vision Workshop, Virginia Tech, VA, September 6.
 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG), University of Washington, Seattle, WA, July 17-24.
 Programming and Computer Algorithms in Animal Breeding With Focus on Genomic Selection and Single-Step GBLUP, University of Georgia, GA, May 7-25.

• Introduction to Graphical Models With Applications to Quantitative Genetics and Genomics, Iowa State University, IA, June 19-23.

• Software Carpentry Workshop. University of Nebraska-Lincoln, NE, January 5-6.

References and additional information available upon request.

2017